welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right let's do some check-ins I'm
one percent nervous I am really calm
right now and I'm excited there's like a
bubbly bubbly mess coming up of
excitement so welcome to the stoah I am
Peter Lindbergh the steward of the stoah
and the Stowe as a place for us to go
here and dialogue about what matters
most at the nice edge of this moment and
today we're very lucky to have my friend
Tomas Bjorkman here today at the store
and Tyson will will formally introduce
Tomas but yeah I view him as the meta
modern whisperer you know I don't think
the whole meta modern scene would be
what it is today
without him he's very instrumental in
that and I think even coined my favorite
word or phrase the meta-crisis I'm
pretty sure he ki kind that and which is
a delicious phrase and it kind of
encapsulate so much so yeah so I'm gonna
hand it over to Tyson Tyson's gonna
introduce Tomas and explain how the city
is going to go so I head over to you my
friend Thank You Peter welcome everybody
Thank You Tomas for being here
Tomas is an applied philosopher and a
social entrepreneur he's the co-founder
of the SKA foundation and the co
initiator of the emerge media platform
which I'm particularly grateful for in
this time and I have come to experience
Tomas as a sort of a guide and a
trailblazer for the the Golden Age
community and answering and asking and
experimenting under the question of how
to create a more conscious society from
the ground up so I'm really appreciative
that he's here with us today he'll be
sharing a talk with us and then
afterward we will open it up to
questions so please answer your
questions in the chat below and then
when we get to the question portion I
will call on you to share your question
so Tomas the floor is yours
thank you thank you Peter and thank you
Tyson for that introduction and I'm very
glad to be on your podcast it's going to
be very interesting to talk a little bit
about meta modernism and talk about
where I think that we are in society at
this point in time I'm also happy to see
a few familiar faces among the
participants so I say hello to to all of
you who I know and to all of you who are
I don't yet so I've been asked to speak
for perhaps 10 15 minutes as Annie as an
introduction and I want to give you a
little bit my personal background and
also tell you a little bit of what I'm
doing right now and then also talk about
meta-crisis as Peter mentioned and where
I think we are in this very
transformative point of human history so
if I start a little bit with myself and
my own background so I'm Swedish I come
from a very modest middle class or even
even lower middle-class background from
an industrial town in Sweden and I was
lucky enough to be the first in my
family both of my father's and my
mother's side to go to university I had
a talent for mathematics and physics so
that's what I studied and I thought that
I would become an academic within
theoretical physics but for various
reasons I come to realize that even
though it's a very strong drive for me
to try to understand the world and I
have during the last ten years published
three books that I might come back to
where I'm trying to analyze and trying
to understand where we are in the world
right now
so that's a very strong drive I have but
an equally strong drive I discovered was
actually to change the world to do
things to to create organizations and
experiments so after University I've
actually been a serial entrepreneur and
started businesses in IT property and in
banking
I built a banking business in
Scandinavia and then in Switzerland
which I sold in 2001 had to commit to
stay as board on the board of directors
of the Swiss bank that bought my
Scandinavian business for five years and
be a chairman of the Banking Group in in
Sweden but when that contract ended in
2006 I had the opportunity to think
about what to do with the second half of
my life and I decided that I wanted to
set up a foundation in Stockholm called
the Oak Island foundation accredit and
we have our own island outside Stockholm
the oak island where we try to both from
a very practical perspective but also
from a theoretical perspective look into
the interrelationship between personal
inner development and societal change
and the reason I came up with that ten
years ago was really from my experience
in business starting to realize that
leadership development consultants in
the business world really was on to
something when they pointed out that
perhaps the most important trait when it
comes to recruiting top managers in any
organization is really a matter of inner
maturation inner growth and I also had
the opportunity to see firsthand how
leadership development programs
could facilitate this in a development
in a growth what I today might call a
process of consciousness development and
I was very surprised by the fact that we
then at least in some part of the
business world realized the importance
of interpersonal development when we are
not at all in society or in education or
in our political discourse at all
putting any emphasis on this lifelong
inner maturation process and the
possibility of consciousness development
I also learned from my years in business
the importance of corporate culture and
in the same way many consultants pointed
out to me the importance of getting the
corporate culture right if you get the
corporate culture right in a in a larger
organization then most things will sort
themselves out whereas if you don't get
the corporate culture right it doesn't
matter what new reorganizations or what
new manuals you you issue and then again
I was surprised that in in society today
outside the business world we are not at
all talking about culture in that way we
are not talking about societal culture
in the same way as we're talking about
corporate culture which of course I
think we should and then of should
mention that I'm of course not that
naive to believe that we today should
have could have or even should have a
monoculture in our society I think in a
more complex society we really benefit
from having many perspectives and having
a multicultural society but a
multicultural society for that to do
evolve and flourish we need to have some
sort of meta culture or a holding
culture some holding environment that
holds the process of forming a
multicultural society jazz
throwing a lot of different cultures
into the bin them and then expecting
them to flourish that is very very naive
so from our business background I had
this focus on in the development and
societal culture and I was very curious
about the connection between these two
to fast forward a few years five years
ago after having had my foundation up
and running for four five years I
started to realize together with my
friend and colleague and co-author Liana
Anderson mayonnaise Danish writer and
philosopher and we together started to
realize that what I was doing in the
foundation was really to reinvent the
wheel again because without us knowing
it and it's not that many people in
Scandinavia who actually know the fact
that one of the reasons and I could even
ask argue that the most important reason
why all of the Nordic countries Denmark
Norway Sweden certainly managed a
hundred or a hundred and fifty years ago
to move from being the poorest non
democratic agrarian societies in in in
Europe Sweden was that poor in the late
1800s that up to thirty percent of the
working population actually emigrated
mainly to the u.s. to to get away from
from starving and and misery and then
just a few generations later even before
the Second World War all the Nordic
countries were in the top list of the
most the richest the most happy the most
stable industrial democracies in in the
world
and the reason for for this rapid
development or even transformative
change in society lien and I argue in in
our book the Nordic secret was the fact
that leading intellectuals and
politicians in all the Nordic countries
actually had a very deep understanding
of the importance of inner personal
growth and development and societal
change and they also knew that in times
of rapid societal transition and of
course they saw industrialization and
urbanization coming that in those
moments in history were had rapid
societal transformation then it's just
so natural for us humans to want to have
an outside authority to hold on to to
hold on to a dogmatic religion or to an
authoritarian leader but these
intellectuals and politicians they
didn't want to be authoritarian leaders
they were firmly committed to building
democracy and they knew that the only
way to build democracy is to build it
from bottom up so they wanted to empower
what we would call today perhaps a
critical mass of conscious co-creators
of modernity and the interesting thing
is how they went about to do that they
actually created what perhaps today best
could be described as retreat centers
they created a lot of retreat centers
all over Scandinavia and by the turn of
the last century 1900 there was actually
a hundred centers in Denmark alone 75 in
Norway and a hundred and 50 in Sweden
where young adults in there
twenties could spend later on with full
state subsidy up to six months in
retreat with the expressed aim of
becoming what we today might call with
Professor Robert Keegan's language self
authoring another way of putting it is
that you you you shift your locus of
control from being dependent on an on an
external authority on peer group on your
parents on your boss to know the values
in your life in your direction in life
to really internalize your locus and
control to connect with your inner
compass and be grounded enough to be
able to act as conscious co-creators of
the new society and when this program
was at its height almost exactly 100
years ago then 10% of each young
generation in Scandinavia went through
one of these six months retreats and of
course that created some sort of
critical mass some sort of tipping point
especially since these conscious
co-creators came from all different
layers of society an absolute majority
were actually from farming or
working-class background so I believe
that we right now connecting to the
meta-crisis are at a point in the
Western civilization at least where we
again are facing a societal transition a
societal transformation and this time
it's not from a pre-modern society into
modernity but rather from modernity
via the postmodern deconstruction of
modernity into something that we don't
know what it is it is certainly going to
be emergent so we don't know what it is
but if we want to give a name to it I
sometimes use the term
the meta modern society so going from
the pre-modern to the modern via the
postmodern to a meta modern society and
just as the transition from the
pre-modern to the modern society
actually involved also not and not only
a societal transformation but also an
inner personal transformation that was
necessary for us to be able to hold the
more complex but also more elegant
society of modernity also more free
society of modernity I believe that we
today are at the same point where we
need to go through inner personal
development perhaps even transformation
in order to be able to co-create and
then hold and replicate a more complex
but also more elegant could even say
more loving metamodel society and the
story about this transition and how I
think that we through personally in the
development can support that transition
that's the story that I tell in my
latest book in the world we create so I
think that could could be a framing and
I am I might speak a little bit more but
that might then be prompted by by the
questions so I suggest that we open up
the floor
awesome thank you I have one question
and I see Peters got a question
questions are coming in I'm curious
about a project or a experience
something that has particularly got your
curiosity and your excitement right now
that is either a physical place and a
project or a social experiment but
something that you've you're yeah most
that's most alive to you that you're
interested in for doing the inner
development that right now is necessary
and what you know about them what you
studied and your work in the Nordics
secret
and these retreat centers to what extent
were they priming people to like go into
the world and do meaningful things or to
what extent were they purely focused on
this is just inner development for the
sake of it sometimes that's what I
wonder about is I'm always doing my
inner work through the lens of like how
it's going to be applied and so I'm
curious about how you think about that
okay so so first to the question of
initiatives and experiments so so I see
myself more as a social entrepreneur
then then a thinker or or an author
certainly I have my my theory of change
and I have articulated that in in my
books but I think that my main strength
is actually in entrepreneurship so I
have started up myself a few initiatives
that I could could mention so in in
Stockholm we have a what could be
described as a conscious co-working
space where we are bringing
organizations together that are working
in this area and trying to cook great in
this area I've taken the initiative to a
similar conscious co-working space
called the co-creation loft in in Berlin
and also a co living space in Stockholm
where we in in the very center of
Stockholm have 55 people living together
in in one property
20 different nations age from 23 to 55 I
believe it at the moment where they are
all selected because they are
changemakers they could be social
entrepreneurs but also just take
entrepreneurs or cultural people artists
wanting to sort of them influence the
world but also they are committed to the
inner developmental journey so all these
people are also committed to working on
themselves but also supporting each
other in this process so I think that
creating such conscious co-working
spaces or cool living spaces could could
be a a way to increase the consciousness
and also experiment of different new
ways of working and living together
another initiative that are taken
together with a take for good foundation
in Stockholm the North Korean Foundation
the Northern Lights Foundation so our
two foundations are together since a
couple of years working on trying to use
a digital platform to support personal
inner growth so we are trying to do the
same thing as we are doing on on our
island and you many people are doing in
retreats we are trying to replicate that
on a digital platform and the platform
is called 29k that's 29,000 that's the
number of days you have in your life if
you live a long and rich life and our
tagline is make them all matter and that
we are trying in this technical platform
we are trying to replicate the sharing
circles that are so important in its in
the developmental work and we are trying
to replicate that in a
virtual environment just like we are in
in right now and to our surprise it has
it has turned out to actually be working
at least as well digitally as in
physical space in some of our users
actually think it is more comfortable to
do these type of deep sharing when you
are at home in your room known and
comfortable surroundings rather than
being in a new unfamiliar place so we
are very lucky there so I think as as I
said we are in an emergent process I
certainly believe that consciousness
development supporting large scale of
consciousness development is nice needed
exactly how we do this exactly what the
odds are when we are at this sort of
phase shift or bifurcation point I don't
know we I can see a lot of things
pointing to there to the dark side so I
certainly believe that we have a huge
risk of this phase transition actually
being a breakdown in the international
system being a breakdown of our
societies but I also see the possibility
of the emergence of a new civilization
and I think that what we can do part
from working with consciousness
development it's just experimenting with
new ways of being together and working
together and then see what is what is
actually working so in that respect I
see the Nordic secret more as a case
study than a blueprint I don't think we
should try to replicate and do the same
today on a global basis but certainly
the Nordic secret tells us that a
large-scale focus on inner development
can
shift coal countries and has shifted
called whole countries for for the
better
thank you Peter will you ask you a
question about the meta-crisis and
everywhere else continue to share your
questions in the chat thanks Jason
yeah so I'm I appreciate good coinage
and I love the term medic crisis which I
believe you coined so I'm curious like
the when and the why of of when you you
coined it and if you can maybe like I
does an elevator pitch like just unpack
what that term means for you so I don't
know if I can claim that I coined it I
think this term has been around in our
in our circles for for quite a few years
and certainly in in one of our my image
and other initiative that I didn't
mention and that is the prospective I
Institute in in London we have been
talking about the meta crisis for for
quite some years so it it might actually
be here Jonathan Rosen at the
perspectiva Institute whom mentioned it
the first time I don't remember exactly
but I think I was the first one writing
about it and writing about it in in my
book the the world we create and
unpacking it a little bit and I just
think it's important that that that we
recognize that these different crises
that we see in the world and that we
have seen for many years like the
environmental crisis the inequality
crisis of psychological ill health
crisis the obesity crisis all of these
different crises that they are not
separated from each other and that it
might actually be that all these
different crises are just symptoms of an
underlying meta-crisis and for me then
that meta crisis is really about our
press
worldview and way of organizing our
society going back all the way to the
Enlightenment that was the last time
when we really shifted our our way of
looking at ourselves and on society and
on the world that new world that
worldview that we got through the
Enlightenment has of course served
humanity very well in many respects we
wouldn't want to be without modern
medicine and democracy and human rights
and all of this but at the same time I
think that that worldview is now
reaching the the limits of its capacity
and that we need to not leave that way
of looking behind totally but certainly
expand on our worldview in in many ways
and in my book the world we create I
point at at least five ways I need no
five directions I think we need to
expand our worldview and just very
briefly it's about realizing that we are
not just these isolated individuals
maximizing our own utility that the
enlightenment philosophers wanted us to
believe that we were of course we are in
some respects individuals and we should
keep our individuality but we should
also realize that we are so totally
interconnected and and interdependent
and that we need to keep these both
aspects live at the same time we also
need to go into a much much more
systemic and holistic way of looking at
the world rather than this linear and
analytical way that again through
Newtonian physics has inspired so much
of science during the last 200 years and
been very very useful but it has to
become complemented with a systemic
holistic way of looking at the world
the next shift
is the view of our mind going again from
the enlightenment philosophers view of
our mind as a rational machine to
realizing that our mind is a an evolving
organic system under constant evolution
throughout our lives and then it's
waking up to our socially constructed
reality so I think that meta crisis is a
key term consciousness development is a
key term but also our collective
imaginary is a key term our collective
imaginary that is sort of like the water
that we see that as fishes we we swim in
we have this societal culture that we
are in the and our worldview and all
these hidden assumptions that we just
take for granted and of course my
favourite example there is the market
that we believe is such a sort of a
natural phenomenon
when in fact even even the free market
if there should be such a thing is a
social construct is something that we as
humans had consciously and unconsciously
created during the last couple of
hundred years and we need to start to
see these things as human constructs
because the moment we start to see the
water we swim in we can start to take a
responsibility for that water and we can
try to to change it but of course the
problem there is that to change our
collective imaginary we need to do that
collectively we can only do so much
individually because we need to be we
need we are all swimming in the same
water and then finally in the last shift
in our worldview is really going away
from this focus on material growth and
utility to really to start to see that
we need to focus on meaning and and
purpose and that is again a shift from
the outside world to to our to our
the world so yeah really good okay we
have a lot of juicy questions so I'm
gonna focus on calling on the people
that received like plus ones or up votes
on their questions to continue sourcing
the collective here and the best way we
can
so up though questions as well that you
want to and then also questions that
build on what's being said so rainy will
you ask your question sure let me find
it
so many good questions on capitalism
Thanks yeah I was um brought up the
market and this move from modernism in
which capitalism is so important what
are your what are your thoughts about
conscious capitalism as a viable
platform I know within that community
there's this sense that if we can be
more conscious more sustainable good
business practices than that then that
will sort of save our society from the
climate crisis and then there's other
viewpoints that the whole structure is
is unsustainable and there's so many
externalities not to mention a kind of
exploitative relationship with things
that it's the sort of spiritual
materialism to think that just by being
good or conscious we can continue living
the way we do what do you think about
conscious capitalism and in those two
perspectives that is a very good
question and one way of addressing it
would be to introduce bill sharps model
of the three horizons that we have the
first horizon that's the system where we
are today we have the third horizon
that's the system where we want to be in
perhaps
10 20 100 years and then we have the
second horizon in between which might be
things that we need to put in place in
order to be able to go from the first
risin to to the third horizon and I
would say that certainly conscious
capitalism and and and other initiatives
like that are very good initiatives in
in the first rise that's of course what
we could do already today in order to
try to make the market and business
function a little bit better a little
bit more just a little bit more
regenerative and a little bit more more
sustainable but and this is my personal
experience after working for many years
within the banking industry within any
industry the market and the market rules
puts very severe framing conditions so
if you want to survive and be in
business in any business being a media
business pharmaceutical business social
media platform business or banking
business you have to follow the logic of
that industry you have to follow the
logic of the market in that industry but
then of course that logic is not an
actual logic it is made up by all the
constitutive rules in the market for
example what can be owned who can own
something what's the function of a
corporation and all of these things so
as long as we have the these forces or
the industries or the forces of the
market working against our consciousness
against our our compassion against our
goodwill then it's only so much we can
do and still survive in the market we
should do it but there's only so much we
can do
so for to really shift business we need
to shift the fundamental constraints the
constitutive rules of the market and my
main point is that that can be done even
more so I noticed through my years in
banking that it is constantly done so
within the banking industry we were and
are I presume even though I left the
industry 10 years ago we were constantly
lobbying on the American legislators and
on the EU legislators to tweak these
rules of the market to our benefit to
the benefit of the industry and that is
happening in the banking industry that's
happening in the pharma industry in the
media industry in the food industry and
my point here was that I was very
surprised but when I saw this in the
banking industry how how many times
naive the legislators were when the
industry was coming with their very
expensive consultancy reports explaining
why these new rules should be
implemented but they were paid by the
industry and working for the industry
and there were none such job done for
the benefit of society
there was nobody arguing well these
rules might be good for the industry but
they are not good for society so at
least we need to have some sort of
balance here and we need to sort of help
the legislature understand that these
rules that we are constantly
implementing and tweaking actually have
fundamental effect on how the market is
is clearing and who is benefiting from
it and what is profitable and what is
even possible to do in in a certain
industry
to summarize yes on the shorter eysan
conscious capitalism more enlightened
business leader more more green and
sustainable business is of course
perfect but but should we have any real
change in the economic system which i
think is evident that that we need to
have then we need to rethink the market
front from from bottom the good news is
that i think that we have help here in
the technological development and
specifically when it comes to
alternative currencies and
cryptocurrencies and things like that
the old market is a very crude but
efficient instrument when we are sort of
projecting all human values down to one
dimension the price with with
cryptocurrency we can do a much much
more refined system not projecting
everything down to one dimension and
thereby keeping more information so we
are sacrificing a lot of information for
efficiency and that is probably the only
way we could have done it 200 years ago
and a 100 years ago perhaps even 20
years ago but going forward we can have
more efficient markets more deeper
markets more current more conscious
markets thank you thank you David will
you ask your question yeah thank you
this is inspired by John for Vicki and
his idea of wisdom cultivation so that's
the context but the question is it's a
statement first the move from external
authority to internal authorship is
complex and intuition in part seems to
be seems to be a kind of thinking from
spiritual mind rather than from the
rational brain mind organizational
leadership and democracy seems extended
rational thought my intuition is that
the next development stage is a
different kind of organization and
governance more like an organism than a
machine and operating from a spiritual
mind transcending and including the gut
heart mind and brain mind does this
inspire thoughts on what individual
development and cultivation looks like
wisdom cultivation looks like absolutely
what was that a quote from John Bevere
that's my own that's my own inspiration
hit listening to John okay yeah okay now
I I agree hundred percent with with with
what you what you said so I think that
just just like going from the pre-modern
world to the modern world was enabled by
us really developing a rationalistic way
of thinking and knowing and again that
way of thinking and knowing has got
tremendous strengths and potential
particularly when it comes to
understanding the natural world so I
think again what we need to do now is
that we need to to develop new ways of
understanding and knowing not of course
leaving the rational way of of thinking
and the science science behind but
understand that they are very very
strong when it comes to to natural
phenomena when it comes to social
phenomenon or even inner world
phenomenon then we need to complement
that way of of of knowing certainly with
with intuition in inspiration I'm not
myself a religious person I I could even
sometimes label myself as an artist but
I certainly think that
this direction of inner development is
moving us in the same direction as many
religions have been trying to move us
and is fundamental in in many spiritual
traditions so in some way you could say
that this crisis is meta-crisis which is
an existential crisis for Humanity the
outcome of that will be dependent on if
we can again access some sort of
spiritual development and I would even
say and I would even say that this
concept of consciousness development
that we were practicing and in the
Scandinavian countries a hundred years
ago they came from the German IDE the
idea there of the connection between our
personal inner growth and and societal
change and societal growth that came
from the German idealistic philosophers
like Kurt Schiller herder von Humboldt
Hegel and all of those philosophers they
were really arguing for what we might
call a secular spiritual development and
as an anecdote the starting point for
leonis and myself research into the
history of this development in the
Nordic country was that we read a
newspaper article from 1889 written by
you could even call him the founding
father of of modern Sweden the the
social democrat Alma Bronte
he he was writing he was 29 years old
when he wrote this he later became the
Swedish Prime Minister three times in
the beginning of the 1900s and he also
received the Nobel Prize in Peace Prize
for taking initiatives to create the
League of Nations after the first world
war but now he was only 29 years old and
he was actually in prison so he was
writing from prison and he was in prison
he was condemned for blasphemy because
he was an atheist and he was arguing for
a secular society and back then that was
enough to to get you imprisoned in in
Sweden but still what he writes that was
that and I quote him and I translate him
freely now something like we Social
Democrats have been too much focused on
the material aspects of life of course
they are important but they are only a
prerequisite the real important thing is
spiritual development and he's using
that word the Swedish word for spiritual
development he's an atheist social
democrat but still he says that the real
important thing is the spiritual
development yes we need to take humanity
to a new developmental stage and this
language was completely new to Lenin I
myself because in in the books of
political history in Scandinavia the
workers movement and and and the
evolution of the modern suite Swedish
society was all about material progress
it was about workers rights it was about
the 40 hours workweek the paid holidays
and all of that in our history books
you don't even mention anything about in
a development or or even less spiritual
growth on a large scale in in society so
of course Lenin IV became very very
curious to see where where this thinking
was coming from and it comes from the
German philosophers and they actually
had a specific name a German name that
it's not easy to translate into English
for this type of development and they
call it building which is somewhere
between formation and realization it is
the natural formation and realization of
your consciousness throughout life and
the way that that can be facilitated
that is called building and to come back
to the previous question that I now
realized that I didn't answer this
building is done for the individual the
benefit of the individual certainly but
mostly for the benefit of society
because with many people in society
having gone through this building
journey you can actually have a societal
culture that is more conscious and once
you are able to realize a more conscious
culture that culture can then in turn
help people and support people in their
consciousness development so realizing
the interdependence between the inner
building and the formation of society
and how these can form a positive spiral
that is really the idea behind building
and and that is the concept that was
picked up in Scandinavia and even if I
just quoted now the the leading social
democrat in in sweden interestingly
enough this concept this worldview was
embraced both by the socialist but also
more towards the right the Liberals and
the Conservatives everyone saw value in
this for different values
on the conservative side you saw that
you saw the value of having a rich
culture richer culture on the liberal
side you saw the value of a bet
well-educated population and on the more
socialist side you saw this as a very
important tool for the emancipation of
the working class and for the building
up of a new modern democratic society so
this was really a worldview that that
permeated the Nordic countries a hundred
years ago then you can ask question
where did all this go and why have we
forgotten it today and the reason is
that we change worldview and that's why
I think it's very important that we
change worldview again because sometime
around the Second World War and they
certainly having being an effect of the
fact that Germany lost two world wars we
all in Scandinavia turned our focus away
from Germany from the the Germanic
philosophers German stopped being the
academic language in Sweden it was the
academic language in Sweden up until the
Second World War and we went to to
English and we turned our focus towards
the anglo-saxon world towards Oxford and
Cambridge and what did we find there
well we find the Enlightenment
philosopher we find luck in and the scar
and analytical philosophy all being this
rationalistic mind and we switched to a
positivistic view of the world where
only what is measurable counts and
anything a of the inner world is
subjective and therefore not really
worth our attention so yes we completely
lost this focus and we now I can
understand why our history books do not
even mention this because from from our
worldview today consciousness
development doesn't make sense we again
believe that our mind is a rational
machine that should just be functioning
is not functioning we should take some
pills oh go to therapy go in therapy to
make it work again and they sort of huge
developmental potential that we used to
see in Scandinavia that that is often
forgotten
and again now yeah and and again just to
tie it all up to what we are doing what
we are doing now and in this society
transition that we I believe that the
meta-crisis today is pointing out
clearly to us that we need to transition
into something completely new their
consciousness and consciousness
development again will be a key
understanding and it's it's gonna be
again our ability to help a lot of
people in many different positions in
society to grow in consciousness that
that will help us to see a more meta
Amata modern world emerge
Thank You Nicholas will you ask you a
question sure let me find it
right thank thank you Thomas first of
all thank you so you would you had
started off the talk by mentioning that
achieving a meta modern view comes after
a modernist view but by means of or by
way of the postmodern view and I don't
know if you're familiar with David
Chapman who contends I guess the
opposite he says that the postmodern
view tends to destroy the an
understanding of assists like a
systematic rational understanding of the
self it destroys that systematicity
without proposing any other alternative
and he suggests that that in that non
humanities educated graduates of people
who didn't study stem are finding much
more difficult to shift from from a
systemic view a keygen level stage four
to a stage five whereas those with a
stem education who haven't had that
postmodern kind of acid bath of
deconstruction are much better suited to
achieving a better monitor view so what
are your thoughts about that are you
familiar with that and I think he is
he's absolutely absolutely right in in
many ways the postmodern philosophy and
thinking is in my opinion a dead end but
it has certainly helped us to to see the
limitations of our modernistic way of
thinking and it has pointed out many
important realizations for for example
the fact that our world is socially
constructed before of the postmodern
philosophers we we took the water
forgiven and the postmodern philosophers
are really pointing the finger too
water so the post-modern loss of her
helps us see the water the problem is
exactly as you pointed out the
postmodern thinking very very easily
ends up in a relativistic thinking we
realize that all meta-narratives are
human-made and therefore they conclude
wrongly that they are all arbitrary and
worthless no we as humans we need our
symbolic universe we need our
meta-narratives yes we will never or no
we will never find in that
meta-narrative out there we will not
find it in God or in a religion we will
not find it in science and we will not
find it in the market so I argue in my
book the world we create that all these
lot of meta-narratives and these
ultimate authorities in the
meta-narratives like god science and the
market when we realize that they are
human constructs we can either be
completely relativistic and just give up
hope or we can make the metamodel move
and say well then we need as humans to
take responsibility for our socially
constructed world we need to take
responsibility for our meta-narratives
and we need to take responsibility for
our ultimate authorities we need all of
these but we see now that they are human
constructs and we need to take
responsibility for them so and here I I
agree totally with with an integral way
of thinking with cam Wilbur's way of
thinking when it comes to that the next
way of seeing the world has to integrate
the best components of the pre-modern
way of thinking we were even we were
just talking about the spiritual way of
thinking perhaps even the prehistorical
way of seeing the world indigenous or
archaic way of looking at the world
certainly the pre-modern
ways of looking at the world the best of
modernity the best of reason the best of
science and then the best insights of
the postmodern philosophy and then
integrate that into some sort of
integral or holistic way of honest of
seeing the world
so yes the the the postmodern way of
seeing the world is a curse right now
but a bird has got gold within it and we
shouldn't just threw it out we should
take the gold and integrate that with
the previous ways of seeing the world
thank you thank you all right well that
brings us two minutes to the hour do we
have a time or an opportunity for
another question Tomas yes for me
absolutely all right Peter that's cool
all right let's see um Steve will you
ask your question hey Thomas is about a
thousand questions coming up now Stewart
after your great talk so I'll try and
remember it what was coming for me is
the I'm really curious about the
emergent potentials of these what were
physical retreats and I'm curious if
those retreats you said that had
emergent potentials were they just
created and they kind of went away and
did their own thing or was the kind of
some structure or container or river
banks putting those retreats and then
you know it's bringing me to two now
where we've got all these so-called
digital campfires and it seems like such
an emergent potential between the
meetings of these different campfires
and what could come in them in the
polarity between people with different
opinions yeah thank you yeah and I when
I hear your question I also realized
that I left another aspect of a previous
question unanswered and and that was
where were these retreats just personal
development retreats or what what were
the more aspects to them and and I think
I answered that by saying that the idea
behind was certainly personal
development for societal development but
I forgot to say that certainly in these
retreats yes
personal development was one major
aspect but then also and so what also
actually learning about the emergent
technology and the emergent society and
and giving the participants a feeling
for that the new technology that is
coming is actually up for shaping and it
could be shaped for for good
so today that would be actually
understanding a bit about artificial
intelligence machine learning other
other things sort of so yeah that there
was a component there of um trying to
embrace and understand that we as humans
can use technology for good and for bad
and it's up to us to understand
technology and to use it so that was one
aspect but then the third aspect which
was also very very important and that
was giving these young adults really the
tools to act incident in in civic
society so they were actually taught a
bit how to set up a small NGO how to
start a newspaper how to write an
article how to argue for for your case
so today that that would have passed
that could perhaps today translate into
how do you start a YouTube channel how
do you write a blog how do you get your
ideas out there so yeah it was personal
development but also get preparing and
giving the tools to become active cocoa
creators mm-hmm so I don't think that
answers a bit your question that Steve
hey on to some of a year and a little
bit I'm just pinging from their link to
the Rosa Parks story that's in your one
of your great talks thing that's
fantastic we have on the cover here a
picture of Rosa Parks together with gift
and shielder them that's a bit of other
or the cliffhanger so why do we have
Rosa Parks on on on the cover there is a
connection to the USA which also I
believe that you will have David Brooks
on the stoah later this week Peter is
that a case
sorry
that something was glitchy yes yeah I
believe you will have David Brooks on
the stove later this week no we have a
Michael Brooks later on today oh okay I
thought it was David Brooks I will reach
out to David Brooks yeah your time
columnist the reason why I mentioned him
was that that he wrote an opinion piece
in The New York Times two months ago
around the the Nordic secret and he also
pointed that to the connection to to the
US and how Rosa Parks has said in many
interviews that what gave her the moral
in a compass to know that even if the
law of the land said that she should
give up that seat on the bus in Alabama
to that white person that she had the
moral right to remain seated was the
fact that she actually had participated
in this type of Scandinavian retreats
and that and in the u.s. so this concept
actually traveled from Denmark where a
guy called Myles Horton in the 20 spent
a year to learn this concept and then he
started four centers in the US the
Highlander Folk School in Tennessee
being the most well-known of them and
these centers played a very important
role in the civil rights movement in in
the u.s. so that's the connection to to
Rosa Parks and to and to the u.s. so
yeah so the the the the building of the
the Nordic modern democracies the civil
rights movement there is something in
this concept that I think we should
again not not use as a blueprint but
have as inspiration for what we need
right now in the world
well certainly been inspiration to me I
really appreciate you Tomas for being
here and taking these questions we've
got many great observations and
questions coming through so this is
sparking seems a lot of insight and
curiosity so thank you very much it's
been a pleasure true pleasure thank you
good Pierre do you have anything that
you want to share yeah I will close up
with some announcements of upcoming
events
but first Tomas thank you so much my
friend for some of this Toa thanks for
everyone with their excellent questions
in Tison for being excellent MC today so
yeah today we have an event at 2 p.m.
Eastern time with Michael Brooks from
the Michael Brooks show against the red
it's called against the web where he
criticizes the sort of the right-wing
movement in the culture war and tomorrow
1:00 p.m. Eastern Time we have an ask
questions with Nora Bateson which is
gonna be really cool and on Wednesday at
6 p.m. Eastern Time we have radical
honesty during a pandemic with self-help
author Brad Blanton which we should be
really cool as well you can just RSVP on
the the website the stoah dot C a and
the stoah is based off the gift economy
it's viewed as a gift for us to freely
using this time of need if you're
inspired to give a gift to the stoah
just go to the Stoics EA / gift for more
information alright everyone thanks so
much for coming today
thank you thank you all